Liam Keegan

Scientific Software Developer and High Performance Computing expert



liam@keegan.ch

+49 176 34687016

www.keegan.ch

Cambridgestraße 5, 69115 Heidelberg

Date of Birth: 19/01/1985

About me

Experienced scientific software developer with excellent problem solving and computational skills.

Ability to work with complex multi-dimensional data, perform statistical analyses, extract relevant insights.

Experienced at communicating and explaining complex ideas and concepts; over 30 papers, conference proceedings and talks prepared.

Experience

2020-present: Research Software Engineer

Scientific Software Center, University of Heidelberg, Germany

■ C++/Python development & teaching

2019-2021: Scientific Software Developer

Department for modelling of biological processes, COS, University of Heidelberg, Germany

 C++/Qt software development of a <u>GUI</u> tool to edit and simulate spatial bio-chemical reaction models

2019 – 2019: Scientific Software Engineer, HPC

Blue Brain Project, EPFL, Geneva, Switzerland

 Adding symbolic math capabilities to a C++/Python source-to-source compiler

2017 - 2018: Postdoctoral Researcher

ETH, Zurich, Switzerland.

- Developing and optimising C++ <u>physics</u> <u>simulation codes</u>
- Implementing and testing new algorithms
- Teaching <u>C++ numerical simulation and</u> <u>data analysis course</u>
- Supervising Masters student Proseminars

2013 - 2016: Senior Fellow

CERN Theory Department, Geneva, Switzerland.

- Developing and optimising C/C++ MPI physics simulation codes
- Analyzing and visualising the resulting data using python/numpy/scipy
- Design and implementation of an open source <u>Python/PyQt GUI input file editor</u>

2011 - 2013: Postdoctoral Researcher

IFT UAM/CSIC, Madrid, Spain.

 Developing C/C++ MPI and Fortran physics simulation codes, running them on HPC clusters, analysing resulting data

Education

2007 - 2011: PhD

Edinburgh University, UK.
 PhD in Computational Physics.

2003 - 2007: MPhys

Lincoln College, Oxford University, UK.
 MPhys in physics, 1st Class Honours,
 Lincoln College Scholar.

Skills

Communication

- Working with local and international teams from a wide variety of disciplines
- Giving technical seminars and international conference talks
- Preparing research papers

Teaching

- Teaching courses on software development
- Teaching physics, maths and computing courses

Software Development

- C / C++ / Python
- MPI / OpenMP / TBB
- Qt / PyQt
- Eigen / pybind11 / OpenCV
- Docker / Singularity
- Bash / Awk / Sed scripting
- Valgrind / Callgrind / ASAN
- Git / Subversion
- Unit testing / CI / CD
- CMake / Make
- Latex / BibTex
- Fortran
- Typescript / Javascript
- HTML / CSS

Data analysis

- Statistical analysis of data
- Machine learning
- 2d and 3d visualisation
- Pandas / scikit-learn / Scipy
- Mathematica / Maple / Octave
- Matplotlib / Gnuplot

Languages

English: nativeFrench: nativeSpanish: fluent

German: intermediate

Liam Keegan - Scientific Software Developer and High Performance Computing expert

Publications

- "Rational hybrid Monte Carlo with block solvers and multiple pseudofermions."
 Ph. de Forcrand, L. Keegan.
 Phys. Rev. E 98 (2018) 043306. http://arxiv.org/abs/arXiv:1808.01829 IF: 2.366
- "Initial conditions for hydrodynamics from weakly coupled pre-equilibrium evolution."
 Keegan, A. Kurkela, A. Mazeliauskas and D. Teaney.
 JHEP 1608 (2016) 171. http://arxiv.org/abs/arXiv:1605.04287 IF: 6.023
- "Weak and strong coupling equilibration in nonabelian gauge theories."
 L. Keegan, A. Kurkela, P. Romatschke, W. van der Schee and Y. Zhu.
 JHEP 1604 (2016) 031. https://arxiv.org/abs/1512.05347 IF: 6.023
- "Mass anomalous dimension of Adjoint QCD at large N from twisted volume reduction."
 M. Garcia Perez, A. Gonzalez-Arroyo, L. Keegan and M. Okawa
 JHEP 1508 (2015) 034. http://arxiv.org/abs/1506.06536 IF: 6.023
- "A comparison of updating algorithms for large N reduced models."
 M. Garcia Perez, A. Gonzalez-Arroyo, L. Keegan, M. Okawa and A. Ramos JHEP 1506 (2015) 193. http://arxiv.org/abs/1505.05784 IF: 6.023
- "The SU(infinite) twisted gradient flow running coupling."
 M. Garcia Perez, A. Gonzalez-Arroyo, L. Keegan and M. Okawa JHEP 1501 (2015) 038. http://arxiv.org/abs/1412.0941 IF: 6.023
- "MCRG Minimal Walking Technicolor."
 S. Catterall, L. Del Debbio, J. Giedt, L. Keegan Phys. Rev. D 85 (2012) 094501. http://arxiv.org/abs/1108.3794 IF: 4.506
- "Mass anomalous dimension in SU(2) with six fundamental fermions."
 F. Bursa, L. Del Debbio, L. Keegan, C. Pica and T. Pickup Phys. Lett. B 696 (2011) 374. http://arxiv.org/abs/1007.3067 IF: 4.787
- "Mass anomalous dimension in SU(2) with two adjoint fermions."
 F. Bursa, L. Del Debbio, L. Keegan, C. Pica and T. Pickup Phys. Rev. D 81 (2010) 014505. http://arxiv.org/abs/0910.4535 IF: 4.506

Conference Proceedings

- "An optimizing multi-platform source-to-source compiler framework for the NEURON MODeling Language" Pramod Kumbhar, Omar Awile, Liam Keegan, Jorge Alonso, James King, Michael Hines and Felix Schürmann. ICCS 2020. https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-030-50371-0_4
- "'t Hooft model on the Lattice." M. G. Pérez, A. González-Arroyo, L. Keegan and M. Okawa, PoS Lattice 2016. http://arxiv.org/abs/1612.07380
- "(Dimensional) twisted reduction in large N gauge theories."
 Keegan and A. Ramos, PoS Lattice 2015 http://arxiv.org/abs/1510.08360
- "Schwinger Model Mass Anomalous Dimension."
 Keegan, PoS Lattice 2015. http://arxiv.org/abs/1508.01685
- "Four-fermi anomalous dimension with adjoint fermions."
 L. Del Debbio, L. Keegan and C. Pena, PoS Lattice 2014
- "TEK twisted gradient flow running coupling." M. Garcia Perez, A. Gonzalez-Arroyo, L. Keegan and M. Okawa, PoS Lattice 2014. http://arxiv.org/abs/1411.0258
- 7. "Anomalous dimensions of four-fermion operators from conformal EWSB dynamics." L. Del Debbio, L. Keegan and C. Pena, PoS Lattice 2013. http://arxiv.org/abs/1311.4458
- "Mass anomalous dimension from large N twisted volume reduction." M. G. Perez, A. Gonzalez-Arroyo, L. Keegan and M. Okawa, PoS Lattice 2013. http://arxiv.org/abs/1311.2395
- "Mass Anomalous Dimension at Large N." L. Keegan, PoS Lattice 2012. http://arxiv.org/abs/1210.7247
- 10. "RG flows in 3D scalar field theory." L. Del Debbio, L. Keegan, PoS Lattice 2011
- 11. "Systematic Errors of the MCRG Method." S. Catterall, L. Del Debbio, J. Giedt, L. Keegan, PoS Lattice 2011. http://arxiv.org/abs/1110.1660
- "MCRG Minimal Walking Technicolor." S. Catterall, L. Del Debbio, J. Giedt, L. Keegan, PoS Lattice 2010. http://arxiv.org/abs/1010.5909
- "Mass anomalous dimension and running of the coupling in SU(2) with six fundamental fermions."
 F. Bursa, L. Del Debbio, L. Keegan, C. Pica and T. Pickup, PoS Lattice 2010. http://arxiv.org/abs/1010.0901
- "Running of the coupling and quark mass in SU(2) with two adjoint fermions." F. Bursa, L. Del Debbio, L. Keegan, C. Pica and T. Pickup, PoS Lattice 2009. http://arxiv.org/abs/0910.2562

Conference Talks

- "Schwinger Model Mass Anomalous Dimension."
 Lattice 2015, Kobe, Japan.
 14th-18th July 2015.
- "TEK twisted gradient flow running coupling."
 Lattice 2014, Columbia University, New York.
 23rd-28th June 2014.
- "Mass anomalous dimension from large N twisted volume reduction." Lattice 2013, Mainz, Germany. 29th July-3rd Aug 2013.
- "Large N volume reduction of MWT."
 Higgs Centre BSM Workshop, Edinburgh University, UK.
 24th-26th April 2013.
- "Mass Anomalous Dimension at Large N." Lattice 2012, Cairns, Australia. 24th-29th June 2012.
- "Systematic Errors of the MCRG Method." Lattice 2011, Lake Tahoe, USA. 10th-16th July 2011.
- "MCRG Minimal Walking Technicolor."
 Workshop in memory of Jan Wennekers,
 Edinburgh, UK.
 28th-29th March 2011.
- "MCRG Minimal Walking Technicolor." Lattice 2010, Villasimius, Sardinia. 14th-19th June 2010.
- "Walking Technicolor on the Lattice." MCFP Workshop on Large N Gauge Theories, University of Maryland, USA. 13th-15th May 2010.
- "Strong Dynamics on the Lattice."
 UK High Energy Physics Young Theorists' Forum, Durham.
 16th-17th Dec 2009.
- "Walking Technicolor on the Lattice."
 UK High Energy Physics Young Theorists' Forum, University College London. 14th-15th May 2009.

Seminars

- "RHMC with multiple pseudofermions and block solvers."
 CERN, Switzerland, 27th Oct 2018.
- "Large--N twisted volume reduction of QCD on the lattice."
 Fermilab, Chicago, USA. 19th June 2014.
- "Lattice Field Theory beyond QCD." CERN, Switzerland, 10th Jan 2014
- "Mass Anomalous Dimension at Large N." IFT/UAM-CSIC Madrid, Spain. 11th Oct 2012.
- 5. "Walking Technicolor on the Lattice." Valencia, Spain. 22nd Dec 2010.
- 6. "Minimal Walking Technicolor." Edinburgh, UK. 6th Jan 2010.

